The wiz! The stars! The music! Wow!
The Wiz is a music, fantasy, adventure film directed by Sidney Lumet.
Dorothy Gale, a shy kindergarten teacher, is swept away to the magic
land of Oz where she embarks on a quest to return home.
Dorothy, played by Diana Ross.
Scarecrow, played by Michael Jackson.
Tinman, played by Nipsey Russell.
Lion, played by Ted Ross.
Evillene, played by Mabel King.
Aunt Em, played by Theresa Merritt.
The Wiz is a 1978 American musical fantasy
adventure film directed by Sidney Lumet.
Adapted from the 1974 Broadway musical, the film reimagines the
classic children's novel The Wonderful Wizard of Oz by L.
Frank Baum with an African American cast.
Dorothy Gale, a 24-year-old teacher from Harlem, is magically
transported to the urban-fantasy Land of Oz.
On her travels seeking help from the mysterious Wiz, Dorothy befriends a
Scarecrow, a robot called Tin Man, and a Cowardly Lion.
Produced by Universal Pictures and Motown Productions, filming took place in Queens, New York City, from July to December 1977, with a cast starring Diana Ross,
Michael Jackson (in his only feature film role), Nipsey Russell, Ted Ross, Mabel King, Theresa Merritt, Thelma Carpenter, Lena Horne and Richard Pryor.
The story is reworked from William F.
Brown's Broadway libretto by Joel Schumacher, and Quincy Jones supervised the
adaptation of songs by Charlie Smalls and Luther Vandross.
A handful of new songs, written by Jones and the songwriting team Nickolas
Ashford and Valerie Simpson, were added for the project.
The Wiz was theatrically released the following year on October
24, 1978, to critical and commercial failure.
Some critics unfavorably compared the film to its source material and took issue with the casting of Ross as Dorothy,
while others criticized the direction of Lumet, who was considered a poor choice for directing a musical.
Despite its initial failure, critics have become more favorable, and it has become a cult
classic among audiences, Ross's fanbase, Jackson's fanbase and Oz enthusiasts.
The 2015 live television adaptation The Wiz Live!
is influenced by the film.
The film explores themes of new york city, dreams,
melancholy, musical, based on play or musical.
The tone is lighthearted.